<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Database | Htedsv Backyard]]></title>
  <link href="http://xuanhuangyiqi.github.io/blog/categories/database/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://xuanhuangyiqi.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-05-18T00:49:24+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://xuanhuangyiqi.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[htedsv]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[xuanhuangyiqi@126.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A general perspective to understand code and data]]></title>
    <link href="http://xuanhuangyiqi.github.io/blog/2014/12/01/general-way-to-understand-program/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-01T00:22:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://xuanhuangyiqi.github.io/blog/2014/12/01/general-way-to-understand-program</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In this semester, there was course called “Foundation of Data Science”, which is in terms of database but pretends to be related to “Data Science”. The reason for my difficulty understanding it is probably that some prerequisite I never learned before.</p>

<p>Nevertheless, many of the views in the course are worth learning and thinking. Looking back to the courses in my bachelors, which contains Compiler Theory, Database Theory, Computer Network, Operating Systems. As I know, the top universities in america are trying to weaken the connection between different domains. Of course it has benefits in some respects. However from the point of an abstract and theoretical view, it does not help the students understand the essential question.</p>

<!--more-->

<p>Such as database, which is a concept, appears relatively late in the history. Besides it was used to deal with concurrence and high-performance operations, it was ever regarded as a general model to solve problems, just like tapes to a turing machine. To be specific, <strong>All the data in the world can be stored in a database, all the operations to manipulate data are via SQL languages</strong>. Here the “Data” is in the database, “Code” is the SQL. Why don’t we consider other languages, like C or Java? Because we now are standing by data, however relational database is the easiest to understand as a theoretical storage, because it has a lot of algebra-related foundations and guarantees. Now we are facing a new problem: SQL is not turing-complete, which means, it can not perform any operations of turing machine. At least, it can not perform recursion. The easiest way to improve SQL is add a feature: “function”.  <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Datalog">Datalog</a> is such a stuff. As we see from the examples in wikipedia, it looks like rules of a context-free grammar, which contains a series of rules. Since each term can occur both in the left side and right side, it may be evaluated for infinitely long time. The key reason of its incredible power is the ability of “self-recursion”. Consider the turing-complete programming languages you know, the common features of them is “recursion”. However it’s not exactly what we need, in order to keep the “monotone” (which is defined for the programs $x$ and $y$, “$eval(x) \le eval(y) \rightarrow eval(f(x)) eval(f(y))$ for any function $f$”), we forbid “not” in the rules. which finally leads to “Inflationary Datalog”.</p>

<p>Let’s come back to the programming languages, the essential of the strong power of the programming languages, is not “if” “for” or even “function”, but “first-order”, “hiher-order”, or to say “recursive” or not instead. Even though “for” and “if” are not allowed, we can still program whatever we want. Functional programming is such a invention， which is defined on a more elementary operation. The equivalence between functional programming and the foundation of the most modern languages – turing machine has been emphasized in Turing-Church thesis.</p>

<p>Now I have to mention “Prolog”, which is the intuition of this article. When we fist got to know the basic grammar of it, we won’t realize its importance, but after we gain the basic knowledge of mathematical logic, we get to know how the language model the world with first-order logic. While formal systems are developed at the peak of the power, almost every scientist believe the logical derivation is the fundamental method to construct the world. The evaluation of an arbitrary first-order expression is referred to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ehrenfeucht%E2%80%93Fra%C3%AFss%C3%A9_game">Ehrenfeucht–Fraïssé game</a>. Under this assumption, if we construct the Axiom System, and Rules of a first-order logic, we can infer everything with a program. However the assumption is not true because of the limitation of the “finite axiom system” and “low expressiveness of first-order logic”. Besides it’s nothing more powerful than any other languages and confusing grammar, the failures of the languages in industrial application may due to the followings:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Despite the conceptual simplicity, it’s nothing powerful than other languages.</li>
  <li>“Intuitionistric” in theory is not equal to “intuitionistric” practically, for most cases in our real life, expressing them with first-order logic may be more difficult.</li>
  <li>The most important: logic is used to express any possible problems, but not sufficient to solve every problem in the most fast way.</li>
</ol>

<p>To understand these points, can really help people, who just get in touch with mathematical logic, adore AI and mathematical logic sightless. However the basic introductions to these fields sometimes ignore these basic but important facts, so that the students who don’t have an deep insight of the fields commit some naive comments.</p>

<p>For the term “generality”, we have mentioned that database is the most general theoretical model of storage. However the tape of turing machine, which came out much earlier than database, also it’s able to manipulate data with transition table and pointers. While the representations of the algorithms or the computing procedures are at very low level, simply by  0 or 1. which is not a really explicit data representation. We can express everything with tapes, but we can not analysis them.</p>

<p>Even we did talk a lot about data, it’s obviously not enough, let alone the code in the title. To understand study computer science, we are usually talking two things: code and data. However in different fields, they have different names: functions and variables, programs and files, logic expressions and facts, classifiers and datasets. They are sometimes equivalent, sometimes opposite, or even they have no differences.</p>

<p>A theoretical machine learning model is often identified by a set of parameters. The parameters is equivalent with a infinite set of labeled dataset, which it can learnt from.</p>

<p>However, without variables we can not say what is program, how a algorithm works.</p>

<p>The most philosophical significant result about code and data is <strong>code is sometimes data, data is sometimes code</strong>. We always say, memory is a storage of data, but without context, we can not identify a 01-string, whether it is a part of program or a data file. Another example is universal turing machine, turing machine can be encoded as data and input to another turing machine. The case is similar to Lisp, the ability of compiling a string to code (called meta programming) also makes its fans exciting talking about it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
